WiFI-BC: Learning Efficient Implicit Policies from Demonstrations via Representative Candidate Actions.
Imitation learning algorithms face the dilemma of choosing between task success and inference-time
efficiency. On one side of the scale, we find explicit policies. They are fast during inference
and obtain good results on a range of tasks, but fail to shape proper policies for complex
environments with characteristics like multimodal action distributions. On the other side,
we have implicit and diffusion policies, both able to model complex functions and capture
multimodality and expert actions. However, they rely on iterative inference processes that increase
latency on every decision. As an alternative, we introduce Wire-Fitting Implicit Behavioral
Cloning, an algorithm that learns a generator that proposes a small set of candidate actions
and a state-action score function. The generator is trained to make a small set of proposals
representative of the score function, pushing one of them to be the maximizer. Therefore,
the inference process consists only of one generation of candidates and a parallel
evaluation for each of them. As a result, we achieve a policy that combines efficient
inference while maintaining high task success. To achieve this, our first component, the
Q-estimator, is trained to score the expert action higher than a set of negative examples.
The training process of the control point generator is inspired by how wire-fitting
interpolation achieves structural maximizability. To make one of the control points the maximizer,
we minimize the error between only the expert action and the closest candidate.
We also maximize their entropy, so they become representative of the complete score function.
The negative examples generated for training the Q-estimator are a mixture of the top-k
scored candidates and either Langevin samples or noisy expert copies. This negative mining
strategy improves the expressivity of the Q-estimator. Including the top-k control
points allows creating an adversarial synergy between generator and estimator, which pushes
control points to high-scored regions and improves multimodal robustness. To test the
capabilities of WiFI-BC, we tested it against the other baselines in synthetic,
simulated, and real-world environments. In the simulation environments, we observed that WiFI-BC
obtains task success results on par with implicit behavioral cloning and diffusion policy.
WiFI-BC is always part of the Pareto frontier, except when regression behavioral
cloning obtains the best task performance. What is more, we demonstrate that WiFI-BC is
capable of modeling multimodal action distributions. For the real-world environment,
we train the algorithms on the Push-T task. We observe that WiFI-BC achieves the best results
in terms of intersection over union and is the second-fastest method after regression
behavioral cloning. In summary, we propose an implicit behavioral cloning algorithm that
combines a control point generator and a Q-estimator to balance policy success and inference
time efficiency. Through our experiments, we demonstrate that WiFI-BC achieves the best
trade-off across comparison behavioral cloning methods. Thank you.